[SPEAKER_00]: So, we got some sutra translations and it's Udana, number three.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, maybe read it out and see what comes up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Three ten, to be more precisely, called Loka Sutam.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was heard by me in this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: On one occasion, the Buddha was living in Uruvela, on the bank of the river Neranjara, at the root of the Bodhi tree, recently awakened.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, on that occasion, the Buddha was sitting for seven days, cross-legged, experiencing the pleasure of liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, when those seven days had passed, having emerged from that composure, the Buddha surveyed and
[SPEAKER_00]: Looking around with his Buddha eye, the Buddha saw beings being tormented by various torments and being burnt by various fevers, born of passion, ill will and born of delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it goes without saying here that any fever, they might bother one in any shape or form, on account of anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be rooted in these three types of passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Passion, eh... towards pleasure, towards displeasure, sorry, towards prolonging pleasure, towards avoiding displeasure, and passion towards, eh... ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or it has to be rooted in ill-will and... or delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... And that's, again, it's... it's important to emphasize that because...
[SPEAKER_00]: Usually, when something bothers us, that's when the mind is focused on the object of that thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if you know that you should be dwelling on the understanding the nature of your feelings, as opposed to what specifically upsets you, you can't help it at a time, because the mind is locked upon the object of that which is perceived bothersome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it actually takes effort to restrain your craving to sort out this particular thing that's both... that's bothering you, instead of... instead of stepping back and trying to learn from the... or trying to investigate and discern the entire situation, the nature of the entire situation, because that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, knowing that whatever might be causing you any type of fever that's bothering you, knowing that
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be rooted in either passion, ill will or delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it has to be rooted in your attitude, not in the object of thing that's bothering you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the... that's that emphasis that's... that again, as I said, it makes sense and and people understand it in theory, but in practice actually takes effort to first restrain trying to deal with this particular thing
[SPEAKER_00]: That's affecting you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you'll practice understanding the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But actually, understanding the nature of things is fundamentally dealing with anything, including this particular thing, that might be bothering you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the Buddha has seen the cause of this, it says here, at that moment, he uttered the the following.
[SPEAKER_00]: This world, having become tormented, afflicted by contact, speaks of disease as self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on the basis of passion, on the basis of action, rooted in passion, all this torment arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: On account of that torment, you are the one being pressured, or as the translation here says, contacted, passa, means, means, means, um, exercise pressure over you, contacts you, so you act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having been tormented, you're pressured, and then, that whole situation is a form of disease, yet, for you, it's the only thing you know, and you speak of it as self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, goes further saying, whatever one conceives, it is otherwise than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, on the basis of this passion, on the basis of this pressure, whatever you assumed,
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever you assume to be acting towards, to be trying to deal with, fundamentally, it's always otherwise than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that means that even if you assume things to be this... the way they are, so to speak, the fact that you give priority to that assumption, the fact that you give priority to the unquestioned basis of passion for your action, you took it for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because of that,
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever you conceive, what's otherwise than that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Being otherwise, the world is attached to being.
[SPEAKER_00]: Afflicted by being, it delights in being.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the point here that I'm trying to make.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the foundation of your thought, of your intention,
[SPEAKER_00]: Is passion, aversion or delusion, eh... that's already a form of perversion in regard to the arisen state of phenomena, in regard to the arisen experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that perversion, even if you think along the right lines of the experience as a whole, you are not undoing the perversion, which means
[SPEAKER_00]: Whichever way you conceive it, it's otherwise than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, your conceiving makes things wrong, even if you try to think it rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like, in the case of Puthujjana, who...
[SPEAKER_00]: What can be familiar, I mean, by heart, all the suttas, and even understand them on the level, but still remain putujana, is because the certain basis of passion, ill-will and delusion has not been undone, has still been held for granted, has still been acted out of.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what Buddha means here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever one conceives, it's otherwise than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words,
[SPEAKER_00]: The world for you becomes the world of your conceiving on the basis of your passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it takes that first restraint that I said in regard to things that, say, something specific torments you, something... there's some particular fever bothering you, and a kind of something that upsets you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That...
[SPEAKER_00]: That in itself, it's already a product of that, as the Buddha said, it's the basis of whatever commences on the basis of passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that in itself, it's already a product of your conceiving.
[SPEAKER_00]: You conceive that to be the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it takes that restraint first, to stop acting habitually out of what you think the problem is, because that's how you keep perpetuating the very conceivings that are making you suffer in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, looking at the general nature of things, as opposed to particular things, it's the first step.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't do that, you're going to be acting out of what you conceive problem to be, which means you are conceiving this to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you are conceiving its being on the basis of the mind affected by passion, ill-will and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the Buddha means here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Afflicted by being.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, being.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, the world is attached to being.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever one conceives, it is otherwise than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being otherwise, the world is attached to that being.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, that's your world.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you conceive it to be, that is the threshold of being for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Bhava
[SPEAKER_00]: pālitaṃ bhāva, which stands for being, is... it's... it's something a putuṣaṇ is responsible for.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something everybody is responsible for, to a different extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why that being can be undone, without necessarily needing things to disappear and be destroyed around you, because that's not what the being is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The being is you're conceiving on top of the arisen experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having conceived it, things are otherwise than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, your assumption of that being
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, it's always going to be secondary to the arisen phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's always otherwise than that, even if it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being otherwise, you assume, or rather, you are bound with that being that you have assumed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, so, you're emotionally bound as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it goes further.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, whatever it rejoices in, that is fearful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever it rejoices in, that is fearful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever it fears, that is suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by being bound by the assumption that's product of your conceiving, that's product of your passion, ill-will and delusion, eh... you start developing attitudes towards that being that binds you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Towards the nature... towards... sorry, no... away from the nature of the arisen phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you will be delighting it, you'll be rejoicing it, you'll be fearing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And any form of these attitudes that are rooted in this type of conceiving, because of that, those attitudes are the suffering for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's then the Buddha goes further.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the holy life is lived for the abandoning of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, abandoning of that which you assume to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, it's important to point out here, when I say assume to be, it doesn't mean there is a hidden reality behind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the reality that you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the acceptance, in a way, is not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is strength and the acceptance is the first attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, for Putrajana, the assumed being is all that's in front of him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, he can now undo that assumption and find something more wholesome to be in front of him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you undo the being and replace it with non-being, with knowledge, with cessation and so on, with dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if that being hasn't been undone, and now you think about something like, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Things in themselves that are independent of that being, well, that's done on the basis of your assumed being.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that's the problem when people start assuming, oh, there is a... this is not real, there is a reality behind this, failing to see that their thought of reality behind is on the basis of this reality, which means in a... in as much as it can sort of present itself as pure and wholesome, it won't be, because it's on the basis of the perversion that we... that the Buddha just described here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perversion caused by passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't need to be more specific than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever further than you assume, you'll be equally assuming it to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even when you think about the pure reality behind your appearances, you end up assuming that to be on account of this appearance that you already perverted with passion, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the holy life is not about finding the alternate, clear reality that will kind of result in freedom from all the problems.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically about undoing the assumption of anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any form of being, you undo that assumption and that's where the... Because you undo the being, you undo any form of attitude towards the being.
[SPEAKER_00]: You undo any form of fear, pressure, engagement with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, there goes...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think the next verse says that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, those ascetics and Brahmins who speak about liberation of being by being, all of them are not liberated from being.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly the point I was making.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all of those ascetics and brahmins, they speak about the divine, or the reality behind this, or, well, even nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Many people use nibbāna in a mystical sense, of some sort of a mystical reality behind the appearances that you need to discover through your ascetic or whatever practices you might be doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to see that, no matter where you arrive,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be another being on the basis of perversion of your being that you already have.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what exactly what the Buddha means here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whoever speaks about liberation of being by being, that person is not liberating from... liberated from being, I say.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the... and those ascetics and brahmins who speak about the escape from being by non-being, all of them have not escaped being, I say.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the other way when you now see the being as a problem and then you just deny it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But denial of your assumption is on the basis of your assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first group replaces one being with another being, you know, find a better being.
[SPEAKER_00]: The other person tries to undo this being by denying it, saying, oh, there is no being, there is no reality, there is nothing is real, everything is an illusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by denying the assumption, they think they found a way out of assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, any attitude towards assumption binds you to the assumption, binds you to the being.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what it says.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of assuming, this suffering arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the word for assumption is upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because of this assumption, suffering arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because of this, because of that, because this happened, this didn't happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you assumed in the first place, all these things that happened, or might happen, or didn't happen, will affect you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, trying to replace it, won't work, because it doesn't undo the assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Trying to deny it, equally futile.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, with the destruction of all assumption, there won't be any arising of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: See this world, afflicted by various kind of ignorance, beings delighting in what is,
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what we have been talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you stop craving for that which the basis of your assumption offers you.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I open up this whole thing saying something bothers you, you think that particular thing must be dealt with.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already a form of your craving that feeds the assumption that's on the basis of that... craving that feeds assumption that in return provides basis for that further craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're craving for... you're not questioning the the validity of the being.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're basically trying to deal with that which being presented you with.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, craving will be abandoned if one starts seeing things with right understanding, and also, it will delight in non-being, trying to get rid of the whole being in front of you, which includes the things that have arisen on their own, that kind of provide basis for your assumption, for your conceiving, as we discussed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you stop delighting in that as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, with the complete destruction of craving, there is the remainderless, fading away cessation and nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: For this extinguished monk, with non-assuming, there isn't any further being.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has conquered Mara, victorious in battle.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's such a one who has overcome all ways of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's it for the Udana 310.